<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second sermon vpon the ix. chapter of the holy gospel of Iesus Christ according to Saint Iohn Preached at S. Maries in Oxford, the 11. of December. 1586. By Iohn Chardon Doctor of Diuinity. Seene perused and allowed.</title>
            <author>Chardon, John, d. 1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852088</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852088</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17393</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17393)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 638:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second sermon vpon the ix. chapter of the holy gospel of Iesus Christ according to Saint Iohn Preached at S. Maries in Oxford, the 11. of December. 1586. By Iohn Chardon Doctor of Diuinity. Seene perused and allowed.</title>
                  <author>Chardon, John, d. 1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Windet for Tobie Cooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached in Oxford.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17393:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17393:1"/>
            <p>A SECOND SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>vpon the ix. Chapter of the</hi> holy Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>to Saint Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached at <hi>S. Maries</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> the 11. of December. 1586. By <hi>Iohn Chardon Doctor of Diuinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seene peruſed and allowed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſtes. xj.vj.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Jn the morning ſowe thy ſeede, and in the euening let not thine hande reſte: for thou knoweſt not whether ſhall proſper, this or that, or whether both ſhalbee alike good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Winde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for Tobie Cooke.</hi> 1587.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:17393:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17393:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AMPLISSIMO VIRO AC</hi> DOMINO SVO CLEMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISSIMO D. <hi>AMBROSIO DVDLAEO</hi> COMITI WARWICENSI, R. M. CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SILIARIO HONORATIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIMO, IOANNES CHAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DONVS HANC SVAM SECVNDAM CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIONEM IN NONVM CAPVT SACRO-SANCTI EVANGELII IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SV CHRISTI SECVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DVM IOANNEM, OX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONIAE HABITAM IN TEMPLO D. MARIAE, DECEMBRIS VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DECIMO ET ANNO SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVTIS HVMANAE 1586. HONORIS DEBITAE QVE OBSERVANTIAE ERGO DICAT CONSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRAT QVE.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17393:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17393:3"/>
            <head>It is written in the ninth <hi>Chapter of the Goſpell according</hi> to S. Iohn, the 4.5.6. and ſeuenth verſes.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>4</hi>
                     </bibl> I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me, while it is day: the night com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth when no man can worke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>5</hi>
                     </bibl> As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>6</hi>
                     </bibl> Aſſoone as he had thus ſpoken, he ſpat on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; made clay of the ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and annointed the eies of the blind with the clay.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>7</hi>
                     </bibl> And ſaid vnto him, go waſhe in the poole of <hi>Siloam</hi> (which is by interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Sent</hi>) He went his way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; waſhed, &amp; came againe ſeeing.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> haue ſpoken heretofore out of this place (men, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and brethren, belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) of the <hi>Exordium</hi> or entrance vnto the miracle which Chriſt wrought vpon the man that was blinde from his mothers wombe at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> not farre from the gates of the Temple,
<pb facs="tcp:17393:4"/> in which I found three thinges to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: An introduction to a queſtion, the Queſtion of the Diſciples vnto Chriſt, and the anſwere of Chriſt vnto the ſame. And now to procéede.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour telleth his Diſciples that he wil helpe this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was blind from his birth: which done, he annointeth his eies with the claye, and biddeth him go waſh in the poole of <hi>Siloam,</hi> where he receiued his ſight. For the firſt, he teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he is prouoked therunto by two ſpeciall arguments, the one deriued <hi>ab officio,</hi> from his office and duetie, and the other <hi>à tempore,</hi> from the time. From his office and duetie when he ſayeth, <hi>me oportet operari, &amp;c. <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me.</hi>
               </hi> From the time when he ſayth, <hi>Donec dies eſt, <hi>while it is day:</hi>
               </hi> which hee expoundeth by the wordes that follow after: <hi>the night commeth when no man can worke,</hi> and ſo forth. In this firſt argument (which hée deduceth from his office and duetie) he yeldeth a reaſon to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples why he did ſo earneſtly beholde the man that was blind,<note place="margin">The firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued from his office.</note> and ſéemeth thus to
<pb facs="tcp:17393:4"/> ſay: ye marueile not a litle wherefore I behold the blind man, the reaſon is (ſaieth he) becauſe <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where note you that the worde <hi>(o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet)</hi> is not ſo to be taken, as though Chriſt did theſe thinges vnwillingly and of compulſion, but rather that in ſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he ſheweth a ſinguler propenſity and readines of minde to helpe the afflicted. And to this end and purpoſe was he ſent of the Father,<note place="margin">Luk. 4.18.</note> as him ſelfe doth teſtifye in the fourth of <hi>Luke,</hi> euen to preache the Goſpell to the poore, to heale the broken hearted, to preach deliueraunce to the captiues, and recouering of ſight to the blinde, to ſet at libertie them that are bruſed, and to preach the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble yeare of the Lorde. Whiche em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage of the Father, our Sauiour from time to time (as often as occaſion was minyſtred) did moſte carefullye ſéeke to fulfill and obſerue. For ſpeaking of the earneſt zeale whiche hee had to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the buſines of the Father, he ſaith to his diſciples in the fourth of <hi>Iohn, My meate is that I maye doe the will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 4.34.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:17393:5"/> 
               <hi>of him that ſent me, &amp; finiſh his worke.</hi> Hereby declaring that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that hee did hunger for more, or wherein he tooke greater delight, then painefullie to labour in the buſineſſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him of the father.</p>
            <p>There was iuſt cauſe for Chriſte to ſpeake of the neceſſitie of working the workes of the Father, for it was now the Sabboth daie when hee made the claie and opened the eies of the blind, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he knew that the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes would be offended. Therefore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the worſt, before ſuch time as he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſight to the blind, he ſaith: <hi>Me oportet operari, <hi>I muſt worke.</hi>
               </hi> As who ſhould ſay, I know that mine aduerſaries will bee offended herewith, notwithſtanding, <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A notable example to learne all men carefullie and painefullie to walke in their vocations and callings. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception all eſtates of men, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, the Magiſtrate, and priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon are vnder the bond of this obligation, and therefore eche one muſt ſaie in his
<pb facs="tcp:17393:5"/> degree, <hi>me oportet &amp;c. <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me.</hi>
               </hi> Let the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter then (whom chiefelie it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne) féede,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.2.</note> (as much as in him lieth) the flocke of Chriſt: let him kéepe nothing backe that maie do good: let him open the whole counſell of God:<note place="margin">Act. 20.27.</note> let him doe the worke of an Euangeliſt: let him bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon: and let the Magiſtrate be a man of courage,<note place="margin">2. Ti. 4.5. ver. 2. Exod. 18.21.</note> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, and dealing truelie. For ſéeing we haue diuers giftes, according to the grace that is geuen vnto vs (as Paule biddeth) let him that hath an office waite on his office:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> and him that teacheth on his teaching:<note place="margin">ver. 7.</note> and him that exhorteth on his exhortation. In which wordes the apoſtle declareth, howe that euerie man muſt walke in the roundneſſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his vocation and calling. And it is of the merciful prouidence of God that we haue helpers and gouernours,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.28 Epheſ. 4.11. ver. 12.</note> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and teachers, for the gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the Saintes, for the worke of the miniſterie, and for the edification of the bodie of Chriſt. Wherefore ſith God hath ſo mercifully prouided for vs in this
<pb facs="tcp:17393:6"/> behalfe, without which there coulde not but enſue a diſordered <hi>Chaos</hi> and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confuſion, let euery one walke order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and painefully in his vocation and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that when we ſhall bee called to the laſt account, it may be ſaide vnto ech of vs, <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.23</note> 
               <hi>thou haſt bene faithfull in litle, I wil make thee ruler ouer much: enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy maiſters ioy.</hi> But if we ſhal burie the Lords Talents in the earth, that is, if we ſhall not do good with the graces which God hath geuen vs, wee ſhall bee throwen as vnprofitable ſeruantes into vtter darkenes:<note place="margin">ver. 30.</note> there ſhal be wéeping, &amp; gnaſhing of téeth. As often then as wee féele our ſelues negligent and ſlothfull in the Lordes worke, let vs call to minde this argument and reaſon of Chriſt to ſtir vs vp vnto labour, which by nature are ſluggiſh and ſlothful vnto euerie good worke, vnleſſe we purpoſe to rebel, and to procure the heauie wrath and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God to bee kindled againſt vs. Ye know that God was very angry with <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe he refuſed to do the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage vnto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4.14.</note> which hee inioyned
<pb facs="tcp:17393:6"/> him to do.<note place="margin">Ion. 1.4.</note> Into how great perils &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers <hi>Ionah</hi> was caſt becauſe hee woulde not promptly follow the Lords calling, who willed him to preach to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Niniueh, it is better knowne then I néed to declare. And truely, worthily was the Lord diſpleaſed with <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; worthily did he puniſh <hi>Ionah,</hi> that giuing place to their own reaſon, would flée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherunto God had called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in which he would mightily haue aſſiſted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the might of his power. The Prophet, in the firſt of kings, &amp; thirtéenth,<note place="margin">1. King. 13.24.</note> that did eate bread in the houſe of another prophet, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the Lorde, was ſlaine of a Lion, and his bodie was caſt in the way. A fearefull example, by which we are taught how daungerous a thing it is for men to behaue themſelues coldly or deceitfully in that charge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto God hath called them. And I would to God al men would learne as by this, ſo by the example of <hi>Saul</hi> to beware, who receiued a commaundement from the Lorde by <hi>Samuell</hi> to apply the Lordes worke, to goe and ſmite <hi>Amalek,</hi> and (without compaſſion) to ſlaye both man<note place="margin">1. Sa. 15.3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:17393:7"/> and woman, both infant and ſuckling, both oxe and ſhéepe, both camell and aſſe, howbeit hee left the Lordes worke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, for he ſpared <hi>Agag</hi> the King, and the better ſhéepe, and the Oxen, and the fat beaſtes,<note place="margin">ver. 9.</note> and the lambes, and all that was good, and he would not deſtroy them. But for this his negligence he receiued a moſt ſorowfull meſſage from the Lord: <hi>becauſe thou haſt caſt away the word of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 23.</note> 
               <hi>therefore hath he caſt awaye thee from being king.</hi> True it is, that in euerie well ordered common weale, God hath authorized rulers to deſtroy <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek,</hi> and to deliuer the poore, and ſuch as be in néede from the hand of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour. Now if they looke not to their charge, but (as Saul did) will ſuffer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malek</hi> to liue, &amp; not onely ſo, but to grow vp in might: doubtleſſe the Lord almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and God of Iſrael ſhal turne them out of their ſeates and bring them to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.<note place="margin">Nom. 24.20,</note>
            </p>
            <p>But happely ſome will ſaie, we muſt do as we may do, and accordingly as time and occaſion wil ſerue. Vnto ſuch ſaieth the preacher:<note place="margin">Eccl. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that obſerueth the
<pb facs="tcp:17393:7"/> wind ſhall not ſow, and hee that regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the cloudes ſhall not reape.</hi> For with ſuch the weather is alway either too hoat or too cold, or els too wet or too drie. The ſenſe and meaning whereof is this: that hee which feareth inconueniences, and ſetteth not forward, when neceſſitie requireth, ſhall neuer do his duetie. It teacheth vs then that we muſt not ſtande ouer long gaſing at the ſeaſon and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the time, but muſt earneſtly and zealouſly go about the Lordes cauſe, and the Lord ſhall bleſſe our labours and giue good ſucceſſe vnto the ſame. Otherwiſe, if we prolong the time and poſt it ouer from day to day, our prolonging and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ouer will purchaſe the Lordes curſe. For as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> telleth the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> from the mouth of God,<note place="margin">Iere. 48.10.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed be he that doth the worke of the Lord neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently.</hi> Therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his ſonne <hi>Salomon</hi> to build the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord (which thing he himſelfe was forbidden to do) exhorteth him in this manner, <hi>vp, and be doing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ch. 22.16.</note> as if hee ſhould haue ſaid go about it quickly, and the Lord will be with thée. Yea <hi>Dauids</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17393:8"/> zeale was ſuch toward the furtheraunce thereof, that it made him to ſpare no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes, but to beſtowe his owne peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar treaſure, and withal to prouoke others to the forwardnes of the Lordes worke: for ſaide he, <hi>And who is willing to fill his hand to daye vnto the Lorde?</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to let vs ioyne the worthie example of <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Chro. 29.5</note> who returning from his father, and about to depart from the plowmen, tooke a couple of Oxen and ſlewe them, and ſodde their fleſhe with the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the Oxen,<note place="margin">1. King. 19.21.</note> and gaue vnto the people. <hi>Eliſha</hi> would not ſtaye till woode was brought, ſo great was his deſire to followe his vocation. So the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Amos:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Am. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>the Lyon</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>hath roared: who will not bee afraid? The Lord God hath ſpoken: who can but propheſie?</hi> Wherefore, when <hi>Amazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Bethel</hi> willed him to get him into the land of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Am. 7.12.</note> and to eate his bread there, and to propheſie there, &amp; to teach no more in the land of Iſrael, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of king <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> the prophet obiected his vocation &amp; calling, &amp; told him that he could not but
<pb facs="tcp:17393:8"/> obey God,<note place="margin">ver. 14.</note> who called him an herdman &amp; a gatherer of wilde figges to ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent function, giuing him knowledge, &amp; with knowledge conſtancie to reproue ſinne and wickednes in all eſtates and degrées whatſoeuer, and to denounce his moſt horrible iudgementes againſt them, except they did ſpedily repent and ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <hi>Ieremiah</hi> likewiſe, becauſe he was in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion dayly, and mocked of euerie one for doing his office, determined with him ſelfe not to make mention of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Ier. 20.9.</note> nor to ſpeake any more in his name: ſaue that his word was in his heart, as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fire ſhut vp in his bones, ſo that hée was wearie with forbearing, and coulde not ſtay. This ſame did the apoſtles: for when as the rulers, Scribes, and Elders gaue them in charge to preach Chriſt no more,<note place="margin">Act. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> preferring their authoritie to the ordinaunce of God, they anſwered: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be right in the ſight of God, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey you rather then God, iudge ye: For we can not but ſpeake the things which we haue ſene &amp; heard. Paul in like maner: neceſſity is laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, &amp; wo is vnto me, if I preach not the Goſpell,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Doubtleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:17393:9"/> greatly is the worthines and authoritie of the vocation and calling of God eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thoſe, who know what God is, and weigh well with them ſelues what on their partes to him doth belong. But on the other ſide, intollerable is the ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or rather the wilfull obſtinacie of thoſe, and litle do they eſteeme of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine vocation and calling, who halt in the knowledge of the caller, who hath called them to this or that, according to his good will and pleaſure. And it ſéemeth vnto me that there can no better reaſon be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of this diueliſh and damnable care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſenes which (euen at this day) is to bée ſeene in moſt miniſters of the Church, magiſtrates of the common wealth, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes of children, Maiſters of families and houſholdes, and that too in all ſortes both publikely and priuately, then that the greater part thinke and beléeue that they are ſeated in the roomes they are, not of God, but either of Fortune, or of their owne induſtrie. But let ech one in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée and calling knowe and vnderſtande this much, that hee is called and ſent of God, applying this ſentence of Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:17393:9"/> euerie man to himſelfe: <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me,</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring the promiſe, <hi>that hee which hath beene faithfull in litle ſhall be made ruler ouer much.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.21</note> For ſith there is ſuch a great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes promiſed vnto thoſe that ſhall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully labour in the Lordes worke, wee ought all in our ſeueral callinges to haue ſuch regard hereunto, as that nothing whatſoeuer ſhould prouoke vs to ſhrinke from the ſame.</p>
            <p>But the world is at this point now a daies, that it is counted a fault and a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter worthy of reproofe, yea and of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be zealous and feruent in the Lordes cauſe: eſpecially in beating down ſinne and reprouing iniquitie, for which are vſed all allurements, occaſions and excuſes to harden their conſcience in the ſame. For he that ſhall deale calmely and temperately, him they reckon a wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fitteſt to ſpeake in the congregation, and to beare rule. But if the zeale of Gods houſe hath eaten him vp,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.9.</note> if he touch the quicke, if he hunger and thirſt the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of matters that are out of courſe, then by and by he groweth out of fauour,
<pb facs="tcp:17393:10"/> he is reputed raſh, fonne, fooliſh, buſie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcréete, and I wot not what. So it is then, the more carefull wee ſhall bee to worke the Lordes workes, the worſe we ſhall be thought off, and the more eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies wee ſhall haue. Howbeit we ought the leſſe to marueile or to bee gréeued hereat, becauſe the example is not rare and newe, but common and practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the godly long agone. <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nebat</hi> biddeth lay holde on the man of God,<note place="margin">1. King. 13.4.</note> that cryed out againſt the altar in <hi>Bethel. Ahab</hi> telleth <hi>Eliah</hi> that he troubleth Iſrael, and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> of the falſe Prieſtes and Prophets is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of treaſon:<note place="margin">2. King. 18.17. Ier. 26.11.</note> ſo doe the wicked rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſeruauntes of God, when they declare them his iudgementes. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelatter, the man of God cryeth out againſt the altar: <hi>Eliah</hi> reprooueth the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that hee is cenſured wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to die) continueth his propheſying. And if wee looke to the time of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Act. 24.5.</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> is accuſed of the Iewes to bee a peſtilent fellowe, and a moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of ſedition throughout the world,
<pb facs="tcp:17393:10"/> and a chiefe maintainer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecte of the <hi>Nazarites.</hi> The <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo crye out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in <hi>Philippi,</hi> that hee was a troubler of their citie,<note place="margin">Act. 16.20.</note> and preached ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, which were not lawfull for them to receiue. The like did the Iewes and Gentiles impute to the doctrine of the other Apoſtles: and therefore they ceaſed not to perſecute them, as common plagues and enimies of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peace &amp; chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Apoſtles notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding did not ceaſe to do their duetie, but moſt conſtantly preached and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt: for they knew that it was far better that the whole world ſhoulde bee troubled and in an vprore, then that the Goſpel of the kingdome ſhoulde not bee preached, or that one ſoule ſhould be neglected &amp; periſh,<note place="margin">1. Pe. 1.19.</note> ſo dearelye redéemed with the blood of Chriſt. They knew too, that their preachings were not the cauſe of thoſe offences &amp; ſects, and therfore they were not diſcouraged, but cleauing to their vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went forward dayly in the temple to teach,<note place="margin">Act. 5.42.</note> &amp; from houſe to houſe to preach Ieſus Chriſt, knowing that the goſpel which they preached (howſoeuer it
<pb facs="tcp:17393:11"/> ſéemed to the Iewes and Gentiles fooliſh and offenſiue) was the power of god vnto ſaluation to all that beléeue.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.18.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> All which examples are to encourage and to ſtirre vs vp to painefulnes in our miniſterie, and not at all to be mooued with the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned tongues of the vngodly, to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in our vocation and calling. For what if at theſe daies (for working the workes of the father) <hi>Ieroboam</hi> his hand be ſtretched out againſt vs? What and if with <hi>Eliah</hi> we be counted ſeditious? with <hi>Ieremiah</hi> accuſed of Treaſon? With the Apoſtles forbidden to preach? With <hi>Paul</hi> reported to be peſtilent felowes, raiſers of ſedition, preachers of vnlawfull ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, troublers of the citie? And to be ſhort, what and if with Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe we be ſaide to haue the Deuill? Shall we therefore faint and ſhrinke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burden?<note place="margin">Iohn 8.48.</note> God forbid. Now that we haue put our handes to the ploughe, let vs not looke backe, for if we do, wee make our ſelues vnfit for the kingdome of God.<note place="margin">Luk. 9.62. Math. 10.37 ver. 39.</note> He (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that loueth father or mother more then me, is not worthy of me. He that will ſaue his life,
<pb facs="tcp:17393:11"/> ſhall looſe it, and he that looſeth his life for my ſake, ſhall ſaue it.</hi> There is none that ſhall forſake houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or landes, for his names ſake, but ſhall receiue an <hi>hundreth fold more and ſhall inherite euerlaſting life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 19.29 Rom. 8.17. Pſal. 126.5.</note> If wee ſuffer together with him we ſhal in the world to come be glorified w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. We y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſow in teares, ſhal reape in ioy. Let <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> then bid, <hi>laye holde on the man of God:</hi> let <hi>Eliah</hi> be counted ſeditious: let <hi>Ieremiah</hi> be accuſed of treaſon: let <hi>Paule</hi> be reported a troubler of the citie, and let Chriſtians with Chriſt be ſaide to haue the deuill:<note place="margin">Math. 10.24</note> The diſciple is not aboue his maiſter, nor the ſeruant aboue his Lord. Let the plowers plowe vpon our backes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 129.4.</note> and make long furrowes: the righteous Lord ſhall cut the cordes of the wicked. Let the kinges of the earth band them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and the princes aſſemble together againſt the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4. 1. King. 22..24. 2. Chr. 18.24.</note> and againſt his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: <hi>hee that dwelleth in heauen ſhall laugh: the Lord ſhall haue them in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion.</hi> Let <hi>Zidkijah</hi> ſmite <hi>Michaiah</hi> on the cheeke: he ſhall ſee the day when hée
<pb facs="tcp:17393:12"/> ſhall go from chamber to chamber to hide him. To be ſhort, let wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (to excuſe themſelues with ſhipwrack of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience) as <hi>Amaziah</hi> vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Amos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Am. 7.10.</note> intitle great and mighty perſonages into our reprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though we had ſpoken ſuch and ſuch wordes which the land can not beare: all theſe notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, let the lords worke be applied: let ech one looke to the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; ſay like as did our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>me oportet operari &amp;c. <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent me.</hi>
               </hi> Which thing for as much as of our ſelues we are not able to performe (being a charge ſo weighty and the greateſt of all) the Lord both by the paſtour and people is to bee prayed vnto, to ſtrengthen his miniſter with the ſpirit of boldnes and conſtancie, that his forehead may be as the adamant,<note place="margin">Ezech. 3.9.</note> and harder then the flint, that he be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid at the lookes of men, but may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into the houſe of Iſrael, and (in the feare of the Lord) declare vnto them the fulnes of his wil, which I beſéech him vniuerſally to graunt vnto all the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours and preachers of his holy word.</p>
            <p>Yet one other thing wee haue here to
<pb facs="tcp:17393:12"/> note in that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that hee muſt worke the workes of him that ſent him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oportet mo operari eius opera qui miſit me.</note> that is, ſuch works by which it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that he was the ſonne of God, and ſent of God the father into the world, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that written in the fifth of <hi>Iohn:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 5.36.</note> 
               <hi>The workes which the father hath giuen me to finiſh, beare witnes of me, that the father ſent me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.38.</note> And in the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following: <hi>I came down from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to do mine owne will, but his will which hath ſent me.</hi> Whereby we are taught, that wee muſt not worke ſuch works as we like beſt our ſelues, but ſuch as God in his word hath commaunded, that we may be knowne to be the ſonnes of God. For our workes are naught, and our doings peruerſe. Our waies are crooked, and our cogitations euill.<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.8.</note> My thoughtes are not your thoughtes, neither are your waies my waies, ſaith the Lord. For as the heauens are hygher then the earth, ſo are his waies higher then our waies, and his thoughtes aboue our thoughts. And this much of the firſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or reaſon of Chriſte, whiche hee deriueth <hi>Ab officio,</hi> from hys
<pb facs="tcp:17393:13"/> office and duetie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond argument of Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riued from the time.</note>Now I come to the ſecond, which hee deriueth <hi>à tempore,</hi> from the time: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in theſe wordes, <hi>Donec dies eſt,</hi> while it is day: which argument or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt is deduced from the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe and cuſtome of men, who when they take any taſke in hand, are wont to apply and followe the ſame in the light of the day, leaſt (lingering the time) they be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented with the darkenes of the night. Now if men are wont to be ſo careful to finiſh that which they take in hand while it is day, which concerneth the vſe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how much more belonged it vnto Chriſt, before his death and paſſion, to finiſh the workes of the father? For (ſaith he) <hi>The night co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth when no man can worke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Venit nox ùm nemo loteſt ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ari.</note> In which words Chriſt doth ſignifie, that he may not omit occaſion and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to worke, for that the time would come when he ſhould away. Which thing too he declareth more at large by a Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: comparing the time of his preſence to the Day, and the time of his departure to the night. Now the day is the time to worke, and the night is the time to reſt.
<pb facs="tcp:17393:13"/> Hée then that worketh not in the daye while it is light, ſhall not worke in the night when it is darke. The like ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude he vſeth afterward in the leuenth chapter, ſpeaking to the diſciples in this manner.<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>If a man walke in the daye hee ſtumbleth not, becauſe hee ſeeth the light of this world. But if a man walke in the night he ſtumbleth, Becauſe there is no light in him.</hi> In both which it is apparant, that he calleth the day the time which in his humaine nature hee ought to ſpend here vpon earth in the buſineſſe of the Father: &amp; that he calleth the night, the houre of death, from which once rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he carried with him his body trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly into heauen. But yet Chriſt here compareth the houre of his death vnto the night, not becauſe he ſhould yeeld and giue place againe vnto Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prince of darkenes and God of this world,<note place="margin">Epheſ 6.12. 2. Cor. 4.4.</note> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before hee had ſpoiled and ouercome through the force of his death and paſſion, but becauſe then (being diſſolued from the troubles of this life) he paſſed to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt, which now he enioyeth with the father till the latter day: in which he ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:17393:14"/> come againe with maieſty and great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the cloudes,<note place="margin">Math. 24.30</note> with a ſhoute, with the voice of the Archangel,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.16</note> and with the tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of God, to iudge both the quicke and the dead: &amp; at which time (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth) al things ſhall be made ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.28</note> that God may be al in all.</p>
            <p>We may not here contentiouſly reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and diſpute, whether Chriſt alſo after his death did not the workes of the Father, or whether yet to this day he be not the light of the world:<note place="margin">Quandiu fuero in mundo, Lux ſum mundi.</note> for the Similitudes of Chriſt are ſimply and plainely to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and not to be wreſted hither and thither. Chriſts meaning is then, that he muſt worke the workes of the Father while hee is in this life: ſignifying that ſhortly by death he ſhould be taken away: who yet to this day ſhineth vnto his elect, and ſtill worketh in them, by the power, grace and vertue of the holy Ghoſt, and will do to the end and conſummation of the world, according to that moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable promiſe of his in the laſt of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 28.20</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hereof we may gather this generall doctrine: that as Chriſt had a certaine
<pb facs="tcp:17393:14"/> time appointed him to worke the workes of the Father, ſo haue we a certaine day and time appointed vs to worke, which once ended and finiſhed, we can worke no more. Let vs <hi>worke then while it is day,</hi> leaſt (if the night come vpon vs) we be not able to worke. But now: the <hi>Day</hi> is the preſent life which God hath giuen vs here vpon earth, and in which we may worke: but when <hi>night,</hi> that is to ſay, when death commeth on, and when the Soule is once looſed from the bodie, wee ſhall not be able to worke, would we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo faine. So writeth <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact: Dies quidem eſt preſens vita,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theophi. in Ioan.</note> 
               <hi>eò quòd poſſumus nunc ſicut in dic operari.</hi> The day is the preſent life, becauſe that nowe wee maye worke as in the day. <hi>Nox autem futurum ſeculum, eò quòd nullus illic poterit operari.</hi> But the night (ſaith he) is the worlde to come, becauſe that no man can worke there. While then we are in this life, let vs not omit the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is offered vs, to do wel. <hi>Seeke the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay) while hee maye bee founde,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.6.</note> and call vpon him while hee is neere. Sirach</hi> ſaith:
<pb facs="tcp:17393:15"/> ſinnes in this life committed, in the world to come. Wherefore, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> counſelleth, <hi>Omnia hîc diſſolue, vt citra moleſtiam illud videas Tribunal.</hi> Set all thinges here in order, that without griefe thou maieſt behold that Tribunal ſeate. For if all thinges be not wel and in good order whyleſt thou art here, it will bee too late for thee to redreſſe them when thou commeſt there.<note place="margin">Hierony. in cap. 6. epiſt. ad Gal. 2. Cor. 6.2. Pſal. 65.7.</note> This is (ſaith <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi>) the laſt time of ſowing. Beholde (ſaith the Apoſtle) nowe is the accepted time, now is the day of ſaluation. To day (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) if ye wil heare his voice harden not your hartes. It is a daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thing in all kinde of matters to let paſſe opportunitie and conuenient time. If the generall omit it, hee maye léeſe the victorie: If the mariner, he may léeſe his paſſage: If the Marchantman, he may miſſe his gaine. And therefore are wee thus often admoniſhed to take time while time is: to teach vs, that if wee take it not when it is offered, when we our ſelues woulde, wee ſhall not haue it. Chriſt himſelfe, as wee ſee here, tooke his time. <hi>I muſt</hi> (ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:17393:15"/> he) <hi>worke the workes of him that ſent me, while it is daye.</hi> For this wee muſt conſider with our ſelues from the higheſt to the loweſt: that one is the condition of the preſent time, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the time to come. We maye nowe doe that, which hereafter we ſhall neuer be able to doe. <hi>Worke then while it is daye, the night commeth when no man can worke, Yet a litle while</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is the light with you: walke while ye haue light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt the darkenes come vpon you.</hi> And whereas it is vncertaine how long wee haue here to liue (for death tarieth not, and the couenant of the graue is not ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto vs) we ought the more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to labour while we are here,<note place="margin">Eccl. 14.12.</note> leaſt preuented by death, we be not able to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the worke which is taken in hand. If the goodman of the houſe knewe at what houre the théefe woulde come,<note place="margin">Luke. 12.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> hee would ſurely watch, and not ſuffer his houſe to be digged through. So likewiſe, if wee knewe when Death (the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of the Lorde) woulde come,<note place="margin">Colloſſ. 4.5.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:17393:16"/> we would redeeme the time. We would amend all that is amiſſe: we would bring forward that which is behind: we would haue our worke at an ende: we would be prepared: wee would not ſlumber and ſleepe out the time with the foolyſh vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins:<note place="margin">Math. 25.5.</note> we would haue lights in our hands, and oyle in our lampes. But for as much as it is not for vs to know the times, or the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his owne power (for them hath he wholy and ſoly reſerued vnto him ſelfe) it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs all vpon to be diligent and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,<note place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note> to giue the houſholde their portion of meate in ſeaſon: and bleſſed is that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant whom his maiſter when hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,<note place="margin">Luke. 12.43</note> ſhall find ſo doing. But if with the vngratious ſeruant we ſhall ſay in our heartes: Our maiſter will deferre his comming, and ſhall beginne to ſmite our fellow ſeruants,<note place="margin">ver. 45.</note> and to eate, and drinke, and to be drunken, without doubt our maiſter will come in a daye when wee thinke not, and in an houre when we are not ware of, and will cut vs off, and giue vs our portion with the vnbeleeuers. Wherefore let vs worke while it is day,
<pb facs="tcp:17393:16"/> leſt the night ſteale vpon vs, and wee couered with darkeneſſe bee not able to worke.</p>
            <p>But out of theſe words <hi>(Donec dies eſt) <hi>While it is day,</hi>
               </hi> a farther ſenſe may bee gathered, and that is this. Many thinke that they may lawfullye giue ouer and worke no longer the works of the father when they be once old &amp; growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in years: and ſuch men ſay, Wee haue borne the heate of the day long enough: wee haue wrought in the vineyarde long enough: wee haue preached long enough: wee haue borne office long enough: It is now high time for vs to giue ouer, &amp; another while to take our eaſe. Let the younger men (in Gods name) take paines another while, as wee haue done, and ſo foorth. But Chriſt héere teacheth them by his owne example, that they muſt worke as long as it is day, that they muſt continue in wel doing to the laſt gaſpe, and neuer giue ouer. For why? It is nothing to beginne well vnleſſe we continue to the end. <hi>Hee that endureth to the end,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be ſaued. To him that ouercommeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſhalbee giuen to eate of the tree of life,
<pb facs="tcp:17393:17"/> which is in the middeſt of the Paradice of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierony. in 6. cap. Epiſt. ad Galat. Gal. 6.9.</note> A laſting rewarde followeth a laſting righteouſneſſe. Therefore did <hi>S. Paul</hi> exhort the <hi>Galathians Not to bee weary of wel doing, becauſe that in due ſeaſon they ſhould reape, if they fainted not.</hi> Likewiſe he charged his <hi>Timothy</hi> to do the worke of an Euangeliſt, and to cauſe his miniſtery to be throughly liked of.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.5.</note> Whereunto that he might the rather incourage him, He ſetteth down his own example togither with the rewarde, in theſe words: <hi>I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Henceforth is laid vp for me, the crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous iudge ſhall giue me at that day: and not to mee onely, but vnto all them alſo that loue his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</hi> For God is not vnrighteous that he ſhould forget the worke,<note place="margin">Hebr. 6.10.</note> and labour of loue. We muſte not then call to mynde, how long we haue laboured, but muſte haue a watchfull eye, and a diligent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vnto the end. <hi>So runne</hi> (ſayeth the Apoſtle) <hi>that yee may obtaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. 9.24.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, We deſire that euery one of you
<pb facs="tcp:17393:17"/> ſhew the ſame diligence,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.11.</note> to the full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of hope vnto the end, that yee bee not ſlouthfull, but followers of them, which through faith and pacience, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the promiſes. And thus much for the firſt part.</p>
            <p>Now let vs take a view of the order and meanes which Chriſt our Sauiour did vſe in giuing ſight to this blind man.<note place="margin">The order and meanes which Chriſt did vſe in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſight to the blind man.</note> The Euangeliſt ſaith: <hi>As ſoone as hee had thus ſpoken</hi> (as afore declared) <hi>hee ſpat on the ground, and made claye of the ſpettle, and anointed the eies of the blind with the clay, and ſaide vnto him, Goe waſhe in the poole of Siloam</hi> &amp;c. Chriſt could haue giuen ſight to this blind man by his only worde and ſecret power, as he did to <hi>Bartimeus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Timeus</hi> in the <hi>10.</hi> of <hi>Marke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 10.52.</note> but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the diſciples and vs all the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the blindneſſe of man and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy thereof, hee vſeth theſe outwarde and externall ſignes and ceremonies, by which he prouoketh not only the minde, but alſo all the other ſenſes into the contemplation of his grace and fauour, and confirmeth vs wholye in the
<pb facs="tcp:17393:18"/> truth of his promiſe. By the <hi>Clay</hi> then which he made of the ſpettle, and duſte of the ground, is repreſented humaine and worldly wiſdome: then which there can be no greater let vnto thoſe that contend and endeuour to followe the courſe and pathway that leadeth to ſaluation. For as the <hi>Spettle</hi> doth partly diſtil from the head, and partly is gathered together in the mouth, by reaſon of the humour of the tongue and iawes, and through abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce cauſeth and procureth the lothſomneſſe of meate: right ſo, the wiſdome of the fleſh ſpringing vp out of the fountaine of our owne braine, is onelye buſied about ſuch things as ſerue to pleaſure and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lupteouſneſſe, and being puffed vp with the ſwelling wordes of mans pride, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the deſire of heauenly thinges, which alone can nouriſhe and feede the ſoule of man vnto ſaluation. And as the <hi>Clay</hi> ſtoppeth the eyes, that they cannot execute their office, which is to ſee and beholde the things which are preſent and before them: ſo the wiſedome of the fleſh (through the groſnes of opinions) ſo cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſight of the mind, that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:17393:18"/> looke vpon the thinges whiche are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue in ſuch manner and meaſure as we ought to do. They that are after the fleſh ſauour the thinges of the fleſh:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.5.</note> but they that are after the ſpirit, the things of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>The wiſdome of the fleſh: namelye,<note place="margin">Ver. 7.</note> whatſoeuer is moſt excellent in man, as will, wit, vnderſtanding and reaſon, for theſe and ſuch like are meant and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the word <hi>[Fleſh]</hi> is enimitye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: For it is not ſubiect to the Law of God, neither in déede can be. S. <hi>Paule</hi> therefore in the ſecond of the firſte to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> for examples ſake, ſetting downe the manner of his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.4.</note> ſaieth that it was not in the enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpeach of mans wiſdome, nor yet in the wiſdome of the princes of this world which come to nought, but in plaine eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the ſpirit and of power, euen in the wiſdome which the holy Ghoſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, whoſe wordes the naturall man (whoſe knowledge is not cleared by the ſpirit of God) perceiueth not, for they are fooliſhneſſe vnto him: neither can hée know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually
<pb facs="tcp:17393:19"/> diſcerned. If then we couet to profit and to go onward in the way to ſaluation, to beholde the will of God, and the diuine miſteries of eternall life reuealed in the worde, we muſt labour to haue the claie of carnal wiſdome to be purged &amp; waſhed awaie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eies of the mind. And thus we are exhorted to do from the mouth of the Apoſtle in the firſt chapter of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim 1.4.</note> Where he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth vaine Philoſophye which then reigned among the Gentiles, fables and Genealogies, which are endleſſe, and which breede queſtions rather then god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly edifiing, which is by faith.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt now, (who is euermore ready to ſtrengthen our imbecillitie and weakneſſe) doth learne vs howe and by what meanes this clay of humaine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may be waſhed away: For he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this blinde man to the poole of <hi>Siloa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Go waſh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the poole of Siloa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> This blind ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did not forthwith receiue his ſight: but aſſone as his eyes were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with the clay, hee is commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to go to the poole of <hi>Siloam,</hi> and there to waſh away the clay with which his eies
<pb facs="tcp:17393:19"/> were embrewed: that ſo the nouelty of the ſight, and the delaie through length of iourney, might purchaſe greater cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and teſtimony vnto the miracle: for the blinde man ſate not farre off from the Temple, begging by the way ſide. And <hi>Siloam</hi> was a well at the foote of Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> whoſe water receiued or gathered togither not far off from the ſame, was called <hi>Piſcina Siloam,</hi> the poole of <hi>Siloa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. in Iſa. cap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Ierome</hi> writing vpon the eight chapter of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Siloam</hi> is a well at the foote of Mount Sion, which at vncertain houres and times doth bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vp through the cones and hollow pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the earth with great noiſe.<note place="margin">Eſa. 8.8.</note> But <hi>Eſai</hi> (ſpeaking of the waters of <hi>Siloah</hi>) ſaith that they runne ſoftly, and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth too that they were deſpiſed: Not that the waters giue life vnto any man, but becauſe they beare the figure of holie ſcriptures. Which ſcriptures of GOD, when without the bluſtering of worldly eloquence they iſſue forth calmely and ſmoothly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the priuy hid caues of godly wiſdome, haue heauenlye force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the blindneſſe of mans minde how
<pb facs="tcp:17393:20"/> long ſo euer it hath continued, and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that eye with which God is ſene, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truly to haue ſéene is true felicity.</p>
            <p>But our Euang. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſetteth down the Etymology or true interpretation of the worde <hi>Siloam:</hi> which is (ſaith he) by interpretation, <hi>Sent.</hi> Through which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he giueth vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of ſome farther myſtery,<note place="margin">Theoph in Ioan.</note> &amp; ſo writeth <hi>Theophilact. Propterea &amp; Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſta interpretatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Siloe ponit, vt diſcas quòd Siloa figura ſit Chriſti.</hi> &amp; therfore the Euangeliſt putteth down the interpretation of <hi>Siloah,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayſt learne that <hi>Siloah</hi> is a figure of Chriſt: ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the father to giue light to the minds of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for he is the fountaine. He is the very true <hi>Meſsiah</hi> &amp; ſauiour ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into the world: he is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual welſpring of al goodnes: of whoſe water he that drinketh ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be more a thirſt.<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.14.</note> He is of the Father made vnto vs wiſdome,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note> &amp; righteouſnes, &amp; ſanctification, &amp; redemption: in whom are hid al the treaſures of wiſdome &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.3.</note> And therefore as many as couet to haue their minds illuminated &amp; lightned, to be purged of the clay &amp; filth of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdom, &amp; ſo to ſee &amp; beholde the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb facs="tcp:17393:20"/> miſteries of their ſaluation, Let them go to the poole of <hi>Siloam,</hi> that is to ſay vnto Chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a true &amp; ſtedfaſt faith, who is the light of the world,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. Ioh. 1.9.</note> &amp; lighteth euery one that commeth into the ſame: whoſe holy ſpirit, through the preaching of the word, watereth the minds &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth away the clay with which they are blurred, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they attaine to the ſight of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial things,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3</note> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of god &amp; of Chriſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truly to know is eternal life.</p>
            <p>But what did this blind man to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Go waſh in the poole of Siloam?</hi>
               <note place="margin">An example of faith and obedience.</note> The Euang. ſaith, <hi>He we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his way therfore &amp; waſhed.</hi> A notable example of faith and obedience. For although as yet he did not know Chriſt to be the ſon of God, yet he beleueth that he was ſent from God, and therby perceiueth that there was a duty and obedience which belonged vnto him. And by ſo much the more is his faith and obedience wonderful &amp; excellent, becauſe that many things might haue called him back fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this happy courſe, had he folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the counſel &amp; perſwaſion of fleſhe and blood. For hee might haue thought this much with himſelfe: what meant hee to
<pb facs="tcp:17393:21"/> anointe mine eyes with clay, through which he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeth beſt of al may be made blind? Or why ſhould I go waſh mine eies in the poole of <hi>Siloa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> an obſcure poole, and not hitherto famous for any miracle? Farther yet: hee might haue ſaide vnto Chriſt, as <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> a leaper, ſometime ſaid to the Prophet <hi>Eliſha.</hi> For when <hi>Eliſha</hi> willed <hi>Naaman</hi> to go waſhe him ſelfe in <hi>Iorden</hi> ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times,<note place="margin">2. King. 5.12</note> he au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: <hi>Are not Abanah and Pharpar, riuers of Damaſcus, better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the waters of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el? may I not waſh me in them, &amp; be clenſed?</hi> But all theſe coniectures laid aparte, he obeyed the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt, he <hi>went his way &amp; waſhed.</hi> The like faith and obedience was in <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God willed to depart from his countrey,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.1.</note> and from his kinred, &amp; from his fathers houſe vnto a place which he ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward receiue for inheritance,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.8.</note> ſtaggered not, but departed euen as the Lorde had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, not doubting but that he would mercifully guide and protect him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould go. The like was in <hi>Simon</hi> &amp; <hi>Andrew,</hi> who (aſſoone as they were called) left their nets:<note place="margin">Mat 4.20</note> And in <hi>Iames</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17393:21"/> and <hi>Iohn</hi> who w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out tarying,<note place="margin">Ver. 22</note> forſooke the ſhip &amp; their father, &amp; followed Chriſt. Though they knew not whereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to they were called, nor what ſhould become of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor whether they ſhould go, nor how they ſhould liue:<note place="margin">Mar. 1.14.</note> and though now the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was before their eies, wherby they might feare the power and cruelty of the enemy, yet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doubting, moſt willingly they obey the voice of Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>follow me.</hi> They might haue obiected vnto Chriſt their vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; calling, &amp; the gain which they got by their painful trade of fiſhing. At leaſtwiſe, they might haue made ſome delay, as this: ſuffer vs firſt to go home, &amp; to ſet our things in order, &amp; bid farwell vnto our freinds. Beſide this, they might haue thought within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: what is the matter that he calleth vs that are fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, men of no reputation? why doth he not rather call rich men, mighty men, men of wiſdom &amp; renowne? Such things they might haue thought and obiected too, had they yéelded to the ſuggeſtion of fleſh &amp; blood: but the ſpirit of God, which mode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rateth &amp; ruleth the harts of the faithful, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:17393:22"/> mightily preuailed, that as ſoone as they were called, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradiction they left their nets, ſhip and father, &amp; followed Chriſt.<note place="margin">Mat. 9.9.</note> In like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner <hi>Matthew</hi> the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as ſoone as he was called of Chriſt, aroſe &amp; followed him. <hi>Matthew</hi> aſked not whether he ſhould go, what he ſhould do, or how he ſhould liue: <hi>Matthew</hi> (as ſoone as he was called) riſeth vp from the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of his gaine, and followeth Chriſt. <hi>Matthew,</hi> if hee had vſed the aduiſe of a worldly wit, might haue thought in this manner. What a fooliſhneſſe is it for me to leaue ready gaine, and to go vp &amp; downe after this Chriſt, who is a poore man and hath nothing: whom the foxes of the earth, and the birdes of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in happines: for the one haue holes &amp; the other haue neſts.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.20.</note> But <hi>Matthew</hi> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no ſuch thing, aſſoone as he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led aroſe &amp; folowed Chriſt. By which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples we are taught to ſhew our ſelues obedient vnto Chriſt, who ſpeaketh vnto vs in his moſt holy and bleſſed word. To obey is better then ſacrifice,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 15.22.</note> &amp; to hearken is better then the fat of Rammes. Albeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes by which God miniſtreth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:17393:22"/> vs his help ſéeme neuer ſo baſe, or neuer ſo ſtraunge to the wiſdome of man, wée may not deſpiſe nor contemne the ſame, nor cal him who is omnipotent,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and bleſſed for euer into the ballance of our owne wit &amp; worldly reaſon, why he will haue this or that to bee done this way or that way: but ought with al cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to obey and follow thoſe waies and means which he in his word preſcribeth vnto vs. The commaundement of God to the wiſdome of man ſeemeth to be foliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but then <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.25</note> 
               <hi>Stultitia Dei ſapientior eſt qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homines, &amp; infirmitas Dei validior eſt quàm homines:</hi> the fooliſhnes of God is wiſer then me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the weaknes of God is ſtronger then men. Mans reaſon murmureth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth, &amp; repineth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it only conſidereth the ſignes &amp; outwarde things without regard to the word of god which is there conteined. Therefore <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman</hi> the <hi>Syria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (when <hi>Eliſha</hi> by a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger willed him to goe waſhe in <hi>Iorden <hi>7.</hi>
               </hi> times) was wroth, &amp; we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his way in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, rekoning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet vaine &amp; ridiculous: for ſaith he, <hi>I thought with my ſelfe, he wil ſurely come out, &amp; ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:17393:23"/> and cal on the name of the Lord his God, &amp; put his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on the place, &amp; heale the leproſie.</hi> This Prophet propheſied great plenty of vittaile &amp; other things to <hi>Samaria</hi> being greeuouſly oppreſſed with extreame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: but a Prince in great fauour &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye with the king, mocked at his words:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 7.2.</note> that though GOD would make windowes in the heauen, &amp; raine downe corn from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that which the Prophet had ſpoken &amp; propheſied coulde not come to paſſe. Such is the manner of thoſe that are wiſe according to the wiſedome of the fleſh: who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould obey &amp; beleue God in his worde, reaſon the matter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, as though he knew not what he did. But this our blind man turned not aſide in the heate of diſpleaſure at what time he felt his eies to be anointed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the clay, neither did he ſcoffe and ieſte at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Chriſt, who willed him to <hi>go waſh in the poole of Siloa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> but yelded to the worke paciently, &amp; to the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t readily, though yet the worke for the making of the <hi>Clay</hi> &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, &amp; the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement to waſh in the poole of <hi>Siloa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſeemed ridiculous to the
<pb facs="tcp:17393:23"/> reaſon of man. His faith did vanquiſh and ſubdue what worldly wit &amp; reaſon might prompe &amp; diſſwade from the ſacred word &amp; wil of god. <hi>Naaman</hi> would not haue derided the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, nor the prince the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> had they bene endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys faith &amp; obedience. <hi>The blind man we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his way &amp; waſhed.</hi> He did as he was commaunded: he beleeued, &amp; to beleife he ioyned obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And what followed?</p>
            <p>The Euang. ſaith,<note place="margin">Redijtque videns</note> 
               <hi>And he came again ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Neither was the blind man defrauded of his hope, neither did the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his Chriſt wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his effect. For as ſone as he had waſhed away the clay from his eyes, his eies were opened, &amp; he receued his ſight. No ſoner had this blind felowe, a notable known felow for his begging, &amp; known alſo to be borne blind, waſhed (as he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) his eies anointed with <hi>clay,</hi> in a water of no name for any miracle that was euer done therein before, but he retourned home, not without great wonder &amp; admiration of the neighbors round about, with open eies &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cleare ſight. And ſo <hi>Naaman</hi> the leaper, after the heate of his diſpleaſure (through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts) went down,<note place="margin">2. King. 5.14</note> &amp; waſhed
<pb facs="tcp:17393:24"/> himſelfe <hi>7.</hi> times in <hi>Iorden,</hi> according to the ſaying of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God: &amp; his fleſh came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, like vnto the fleſh of a litle child, &amp; he was cleane. Whereby wee are taught this much, that if ſimply &amp; truly we beleeue the word of the lord, &amp; follow that courſe &amp; way which in his word he reuealeth vnto vs, he will grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs the things which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, he wil giue vs his manifold graces, &amp; the ſame in a good &amp; large meaſure preſſed down, ſhaken togither &amp; ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning ouer, in his abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mercy will he poure into our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes. The time is paſt, and therefore I will héere make an end.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <p>GOD for his ſonnes ſake Ieſus Chriſt giue vs all the grace dutifully to conſider of our ſeuerall vocations and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and to worke the works of the Father while it is day, remembring the ſhortnes of the daies and times whiche we haue here to liue: and that we may worthely imitate and follow the example of this blind man in ſuch things as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the rule of faith, to the increaſe of obedience &amp; to the maintenance of our owne ſafety: that wee neither affirme nor thinke that to be vaine, vnprofitable, or hurtful, which Chriſt in his holy word expreſly and plainly commandeth vs to doe. For they which obey the voice of Chriſt, are illuminated with his ſpirit, they are guided by his grace, they profit daily more &amp; more, til they grow vp into him which is the head, Chriſt the head of his Church:<note place="margin">Eph. 4.15.</note> who ſofteneth the hearts of the hardned, vnſealeth the ears of the deaf, opneth the eies of the bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, &amp; ioineth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> togither by ioints to a ful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth the whole body may riſe vp vnto perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the fulneſſe of immortality, to reigne with our <hi>Siloa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Chriſt Ieſus in eternal glory. Whereunto the Lord our God bring vs al to the euerlaſting praiſe of his mercy: to whom with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt triple in perſon and one in ſubſtance, bee all honour glory and praiſe, both now and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17393:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
